A Guide to the John T. Harris Papers, 1771-1937 (bulk 1850-1900)
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
John T. Harris Papers, 1771-1937 (bulk 1850-1900)
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
2025
7 Hollinger boxes and 2 oversized folders; approximately 2.95 linear feet
The John T. Harris Papers, 1771-1937, consist of a large number of personal and political documents relevant to the life and career of John T. Harris. The bulk of the collection is comprised of letters of John T. Harris and his family, and of Peyton Randolph and his family. Several letters discuss Southern secession and the American Civil War. Also included are Randolph family letters, James Clarkson Papers, Civil War documents and Harris genealogy.
John T. Harris
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Placed on deposit according to a Nov. 1985 contract with the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society.
Biographical Information
John T. Harris (1823-1899) was perhaps one of the most prominent citizens of Rockingham County throughout the nineteenth century. The son of Nathan and Ann Harris, he was commonwealth's attorney for Rockingham County from 1852 to 1859, and in 1856 served as a Presidential elector for James Buchanan. Thereafter, he served in the United States Congress from 1859 until the outbreak of the Civil War. Despite his strong Unionist sentiments and his continual efforts to keep Virginia in the Union, Harris remained loyal to Virginia when she seceded in May 1861. During the war he served two terms in the Virginia General Assembly. Following the war John T. Harris was judge of the 12th judicial circuit, which included Rockingham County. In 1870 he was again elected to Congress and was continuously re-elected until 1880, after which he resumed his law practice in Harrisonburg. John T. Harris returned to politics in 1889 as a rival of P.W. McKinney for the Democratic nomination for the governorship. Later he was appointed by Governor McKinney as one of the representatives for Virginia to the World's Columbian Exposition in 1892. He died in Harrisonburg, October 14, 1899.
In addition to the Harris family letters, there are a large number of miscellaneous letters (3 Hollinger boxes) of the related Peyton Randolph Family. The Randolph family papers came into the Harris family when John T. Harris's son, John T. Harris, Jr., married Peyton Randolph's daughter, Mary Elizabeth Randolph. Born in Washington, D.C. in 1833, Peyton was the son of James Innes Randolph, a congressional clerk, and Susan Armistead Randolph. However, despite the numerous letters to him, little is known about Peyton Randolph. Prior to the Civil War he attended Columbian College (now George Washington University) and was an engineer on numerous railroad projects in Virginia, Indiana, and Alabama through the 1850's. He enlisted in the army in Mobile, Alabama, at the outbreak of war and served as an engineer in Pickett's division, rising to the rank of major by 1865. Thereafter, even less is known of his life. He married Mary Fisher following the war, returned to the engineering profession, and died November 28, 1888.
Scope and Content
The John T. Harris Papers, 1771-1937 (bulk 1850-1900), consists of seven Hollinger boxes and two oversize folders (2.95 linear feet). [It is also available on microfilm; see Contents List.] Although the collection contains a large number of personal and political documents relevant to the life and career of John T. Harris, the bulk of the collection is comprised of letters of John T. Harris and his family, and of Peyton Randolph and his family. A small number of James Clarkson papers are also present. The collection is arranged in five series: Letters, Personal and Family Papers, Political Papers, Miscellaneous and Oversize. Brief descriptions follow here. Notable items are listed under their appropriate folder in the contents list.
Series I, Letters, 1831-1937, is arranged chronologically in four subseries:
The John T. Harris letters, 1841-1899, n.d., consist of letters from his constituents requesting personal favors. Letters from 1860 to 1861 primarily address the issue of Virginia seceding from the Union. Echoing the sentiments of many residents of western Virginia, most of the letters express pro-Unionist feelings and encourage Harris to work for a compromise in Congress to avert violent conflict. Moreover, the contents of these letters suggest that Harris worked with and may have been a close friend of Stephen A. Douglas.
Harris Family Letters, 1831-1937, consist chiefly of letters among various members of the Harris family, and provide descriptions of family life. However, there are several letters to John T. Harris, Jr., from Presidents Woodrow Wilson and Theodore Roosevelt.
The Peyton Randolph Letters, 1846-1884, consist of letters from several college friends and Peyton Randolph's immediate family. Notable among these are letters from college friend Henry Force. Force was the son of historian Peter Force and acted as surveyor on the Border Commission dispatched to study the newly acquired lands in present-day New Mexico and Arizona. In a series of letters to Peyton from 1848 to 1853, Force describes his encounters with Mexican soldiers and Apache Indians, as well as his duties on the trek from New Orleans to San Diego. Transcriptions are available for eight of Force's letters, 1848-1851.
Randolph Family Letters, 1837-1928, include letters to Peyton and his sisters, Mollie, Nannie and Sue, from their mother, Susan Armistead Randolph, correspondance between the siblings, as well as a few miscellaneous items of Peyton Randolph's including a book of psalms which he carried during the Civil War. The letters from Susan Armistead Randolph form the bulk of this subseries. In her weekly four-page letters Mrs. Randolph describes life in Washington, D.C. during the 1850's, including the inauguration of Franklin Pierce and the funeral of Henry Clay. Susan Randolph was acutely aware of the political climate of her era and took particular interest in the Know-Nothing party in the 1850's. In several letters she outlines the platform of the Know-Nothings and even urges Peyton to join the party. However, despite her vivid political commentaries and her proximity to the arena of the conflict, she does not mention the issue of slavery. In addition to her political and social sketches, she provides detailed accounts of family life, including rather grisly descriptions of the deaths of various family members. Her letters from Richmond during the war describe the changes in life in that city through the course of the war and include detailed examples of the rampant inflation of prices on common goods such as bacon and flour. Of particular interest are Mrs. Randolph's inquiries concerning her first cousin, General Lewis Armistead, who was said to be the first Confederate soldier to cross into Union lines during Pickett's Charge at the battle of Gettysburg. See Randolph Harris Moulton's Some Randolphs Around Civil War Times for transcriptions of some of the Payton Randolph letters.
Series II, Personal and Family Papers, 1843-1936, n.d., is arranged topically and contains a variety of materials. General papers include John T. Harris's law license, an 1861 will, and his post-Civil War oath of allegiance to the U.S. [A certificate in which President Benjamin Harris appoints Harris as Virginia's representative at the World's Columbian Exposition of 1892 is located in the oversize miscellaneous file.] Also in this series is a photocopy of his handwritten 1898 autobiography, which gives many particulars of his life, as well as a photocopy of his son John T. Harris, Jr.'s typed 1936 autobiography, which includes characterizations of the lawyers with which the younger Harris was acquainted. Genealogical notes and charts as well as newspaper clippings pertaining to the Harris family are also present.
Series III, Political Papers, 1856-1896, n.d., consists primarily of copies of John T. Harris' Congressional speeches as well as several made by other members of Congress. The most notable of these is the resignation speech of Preston B. "Bully" Brookes, who was censured by Congress for caning Charles Sumner in 1856. In addition, there are election returns from elections in which Harris was a candidate. These include reports from Rockingham County and localities throughout the Shenandoah Valley. A large number of political broadsides, handbills and selected pages from newspapers regarding local and national elections are housed in Series V, Oversize.
Series IV, Miscellaneous, 1771-1933, n.d., contains a variety of materials, including general miscellany and receipts, Civil War documents, indentures, James Clarkson Papers, photographs and undated material. Among the Civil War documents are requests for exemption from military service, requisition receipts from Confederate military authorities, contracts between individuals and their military substitutes, and requests to John T. Harris for release from Union prisoner-of-war camps. The James Clarkson Papers primarily are comprised of legal documents from Albemarle County. These documents were preserved by John T. Harris's wife, Virginia Harris, who was a descendent of James Clarkson. Among the photographs is a print of Peyton Randolph and his four brothers, a photographed portrait of James Innes, and photographs of John T. Harris's writing desk, a young Isabelle Heard, and an unidentified young girl. Undated material consists of any items in this series that may be undated, including print material, notes, memoranda, receipts, various lists, writings, and calling cards.
Series V, Oversize, 1821-1900, consists of two folders. One folder contains oversized items such as political broadsides, handbills, and selected pages from newspapers regarding local and national elections from Series III, Political Papers. The second folder contains oversized items from Series IV, Miscellaneous. Materials include a certificate signed by Benjamin Harrison appointing him as Virginia's representative at the World's Columbian Exposition of 1892; a land grant to Joel S. Graves signed by Governor Thomas M. Randolph; and a sheet dated March 11, 1861, signed by members of the provisional government of secession (Civil War) from South Carolina, Georgia, Florida and Alabama.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series
I. Letters, 1831-1937, n.d.
A.) John T. Harris Letters, 1845-1899
B.) Harris Family Letters, 1831-1937
C.) Peyton Randolph Letters, 1846-1884
D.) Randolph Family Letters, 1837-1928
II. Personal and Family Papers, 1843-1936, n.d.
III. Political Papers, 1856-1896, n.d.
IV. Miscellaneous, 1771-1933, n.d.
V. Oversize, 1821-1900
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Boatner, Mark Mayo.Civil War Dictionary. New York: David McKay Co., Inc., 1959.
Dabney, Virginius. Virginia: The New Dominion. Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1971.
Daniels, Jonathan. The Randolphs of Virginia. New York: Doubleday, 1972.
Johnson, Allen and Malone, Dumas, ed. Dictionary of American Biography. Vol. VI. NY: Scribner's Sons, 1931.
Krick, Robert K. Lee's Colonels: A Biographical Register of the Field Officers of the Army of Northern Virginia. Dayton, Ohio: Press of Morningside Bookshop, 1979.
Members of Congress Since 1789. Congressional Quarterly, Inc., 1977.
The National Cyclopedia of American Biography. Vol. XIX. NY: Charles T. White and Co., 1926.
Tewksbury, Donald G. The Founding of American Colleges and Universities Before the Civil War. NY: Archon Books, 1965.
Wakelyn, Jon L. Biographical Dictionary of the Confederacy. Westport, CN: Greenwood, 1977.
Wayland, John W. A History of Rockingham County, Virginia. Dayton, VA: Ruebush-Elkins, 1912.
Related Material
The collection is also available on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.
Harter, Dale F. Of Men and Measures: The Memoirs of John T. Harris of Virginia. M.A. Thesis, University of South Carolina, 1999.
Contents List (Box: Folder)
- Click here for microfilm contents.
- Series 1: Letters, 1831-1937, n.d.:
  - John T. Harris Letters, 1845-1899:
    - 1845-1860 (100 letters) (Box-folder 1:1)
      Notable Letters:
      2 Feb. 1857, Arch Graham on national, state and local politics, with letter of 20 July from John T. Harris (son) interpreting the meaning of the letter
      3 March 1860 Supporter of Stephen A. Douglas and "squatter sovereignty."
      2 May 1860 Talk of secession
      30 Oct. 1860 England blamed for dissolution of the Union
      1 Dec. 1860 South Carolina resident gives plans of that state with regards to the Union.
      16 Dec. 1860 Harris believes Union must be preserved.
    - January 1861 (37 letters) (Box-folder 1:2)
      21 Jan. Constituent blames "Black Republicans" and Lincoln for conflict between the North and South
    - February 1861 (67 letters) (Box-folder 1:3)
      Notable Letters
      20 Feb. Letter from Gov. John Letcher
      21 Feb. Constituent refers to slavery as the "never ending nigger question"
      27 Feb. Letter from Col. David B. Bimey, son of abolitionist James G. Bime
    - March 1861-December 1864 (90 letters) (Box-folder 1:4)
    - 1865-1866 (79 letters) (Box-folder 1:5)
    - 1867-1868 (37 letters) (Box-folder 1:6)
    - 1869 (90 letters) (Box-folder 1:7)
    - 1870-1872 (100 letters) (Box-folder 1:8)
    - 1873-1877 (58 letters) (Box-folder 2:1)
    - 1878-1880 (110 letters) (Box-folder 2.2)
    - 1881-1885 (81 letters) (Box-folder 2:3)
    - 1886 (77 letters) (Box-folder 2:4)
    - 1887-1888 (41 letters) (Box-folder 2:5)
    - 1889 (68 letters) (Box-folder 2:6)
    - 1890-1893 (42 letters) (Box-folder 2:7)
    - 1894-1899 (57 letters) (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Undated Letters (57 letters) (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Harris Family Letters, 1831-1937:
    - 1831-1879 (79 letters) (Box-folder 3:1)
    - 1880-1890 (60 letters) (Box-folder 3:2)
    - 1891-1901 (70 letters) (Box-folder 3:3)
    - 1902-1911 (Box-folder 3:4)
    - 1912-1915 (67 letters) (Box-folder 3:5)
      13, 18 July 1912 Letters from Woodrow Wilson
      25 Oct., 17 Nov. 1915 Letters from Teddy Roosevelt
    - 1916-1927 (60 letters) (Box-folder 3:6)
    - 1928-1931 (79 letters) (Box-folder 3:7)
    - 1932-1937 (67 letters) (Box-folder 3:8)
    - Undated Letters (54 letters) (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Peyton Randolph Letters, 1846-1884:
    - 1846-1851 (39 letters) (Box-folder 4:1)
      Eight letters in this folder from Henry Force to Peyton Randolph, 1848-1851, are available in transcription (NOT ON MICROFILM)
      17 Aug. 1850 Henry Force describes voyage from New York to Havana and New Orleans.
      7 Sept. 1850 Henry Force's duties as surveyor on Border Commission in Victoria, Texas.
      5 April 1850 Samuel Force giving views of a Princeton Freshman.
      29 June 1851 Henry Force describes encounters with Mexicans and Apaches in New Mexico.
    - 1852 (41 letters) (Box-folder 4:2)
      9 March Henry Force describe duties and life in San Diego and survey of the Gila River.
      21 March Susan Randolph, Peyton's mother, notes new painting in Capitol Rotunda-Washington Crossing the Delaware.
      4 July Mother describes Henry Clay's funeral.
      3 Oct. Mother describes father's involvement in Whig vs. Democrat politics.
    - 1853 (January-June) (30 letters) (Box-folder 4:3)
      2 Jan. Mother describes death of Nannie's son, Randolph, of scarlet fever.
      4 Jan. Mother describes death of Peyton's grandfather.
      9 Jan. Mother describes erecting of statue of Andrew Jackson with speech by Stephen A. Douglas.
      6 Feb. Mother anticipates somber character of Franklin Pierce's inauguration because of recent death of his only son.
      13 Feb. Henry Force describes Apache attack on return trip from El Paso.
      13 March Mother describes Pierce's inauguration.
      22 May Mother describes 25th wedding anniversary.
    - 1853 (July-December) (22 letters) (Box-folder 4:4)
      21 Nov. James Innes Randolph asks for $200 to avoid foreclosure on house and sale of furniture.
    - 1854 (January-June) (27 letters) (Box-folder 4:5)
      28 May Father believes Kansas-Nebraska Act will make Northerners refuse to enforce the Fugitive Slave Law.
      18 June Mother urges Peyton to join the Know-Nothings.
      26 June Mother notes rumor that Pope's nuncio was engaged in Catholic atrocities to subvert the government and make Washington the headquarters of the Pope.
    - 1854 (July-December) (14 letters) (Box-folder 4:6)
      23 July Mother describes spread of cholera in Washington.
      19 Nov. Mother describes financial panic in Washington.
    - 1855 (36 letters) (Box-folder 4:7)
      1 March Mother gives vivid description of Grandmother's death.
      10 May Wm. Titcomb warns Peyton not to join Know-Nothings.
      22 Dec. Wm. Titcomb anticipates arrival of Santa Claus.
    - 1856 (29 letters) (Box-folder 5:1)
      9 July Henry Force describes trial of Preston Brookes for assault of Sumner in the Senate.
      17 Aug. Henry Force discusses maintenance of Washington Territory boundary.
      24 Aug. Father tries unsuccessfully to get a clerkship at Congress.
      3 Sept. Henry Force describes his father's (Peter Force) problems with his documentary history of America.
      3 Nov. Peyton believes Buchanan will defeat Fillmore in presidential election.
    - 1857-1860 (41 letters) (Box-folder 5:2)
      7 June 1857 Peyton in Mississippi gladly notes absence of foreigners and Yankees.
    - 1861-1862 (32 letters) (Box-folder 5:3)
      6 Jan. 1861 Peyton believes conflict between South Carolina and the U.S. will not last long because neither can afford a war.
      17 March 1861 Mother believes Lincoln will preserve peace.
      24 March 1861 Peyton joins the Army at Fort Morgan, Alabama.
      24 March 1861 Mother observes that most Know-Nothings have switched to the Republicans.
      14 April 1861 Mother says, "Hurrah for the Southern Confederacy."
      8 Sept. 1861 Mother describes rising prices in Richmond. Peyton's brother John could see the Capitol rotunda on picket duty outside Washington.
      20 Oct. 1861 Mother visits Richmond hospitals filled with soldiers.
      5 May 1862 Mother describes Confederate evacuation of Yorktown and Norfolk. Notes Merrimac is in the James River.
      24 Dec. 1862 Peyton asks when General. Armistead's uniforms will be ready.
    - 1863-1884 (25 letters) (Box-folder 5:4)
      15 Feb. 1863 Prices sky rocketing in Richmond.
      14 July 1863 Mother believes Lewis Armistead still alive despite rumors of his death at Gettysburg.
      20 Aug. 1863 Mother questions fate of General. Armistead.
      17 July 1864 Mother describes scarcity of food in Richmond.
    - Undated Letters (42 letters) (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Randolph Family Letters, 1837-1928:
    - 1837-1857 (36 letters) (Box-folder 5:6)
      6 July 1854 Birthday letter to Mary Fisher, Peyton's future wife. Advises her what to look for in a husband.
      10 Feb. 1856 Letter to Innes Randolph at Hobart College, New York.
    - 1861-1866 (39 letters) (Box-folder 5:7)
      4 Dec. 1861 John Randolph describes winter camp life in the army and his efforts to stay warm.
      6 Feb. 1862 Mollie, fearing that the North will win, wonders why England and France will not recognize the Confederacy.
      12 Aug. 1863 Mother unsure of Lewis Armistead's fate. Notes the high cost of wood and coal.
      22 Nov. 1863 Mother describes death of James Innes Randolph.
      13 May 1864 Family wakes to booming cannon outside Richmond. John brought home wounded in thigh.
    - 1868-1928 (47 letters) (Box-folder 5:8)
    - Undated Letters (56 letters) (Box-folder 5:9)
    - Miscellany, 1844-1865 (7 items) (Box-folder 5:10)
- Series II: Personal and Family Papers, 1843-1936, n.d.:
  - General Papers, 1843-1887 (21 items) (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Autobiography of J.T. Harris, 1898 (116 pages) (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Autobiography of J.T. Harris, Jr., 1936 (47 pages) (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Harris Genealogy:
    - Part I (44 items) (Box-folder 6:4)
    - Part II (31 items) (Box-folder 6:5)
    - Part III (21 items) (Box-folder 6:6)
  - News clippings:
    - Part I (18 items) (Box-folder 6:7)
    - Part II (57 items) (Box-folder 6:8)
    - Part III (19 items) (Box-folder 6:9)
- Series III: Political Papers, 1856-1896, n.d.:
  - 1856-1896 (55 items) (Box-folder 7:1)
    Notable Items:
    1856 Resignation speech of Congressman Preston B. Brookes.
  - Undated Material (28 items) (Box-folder 7:2)
- Series IV: Miscellaneous 1771-1933, n.d.:
  - General Miscellany:
    - 1795-1863 (86 items) (Box-folder 7:3)
      1795 List of Subscribers to the "New Virginia Justice"
    - 1864-1933 (81 items) (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Civil War Documents:
    - 1861-1863 (45 items) (Box-folder 7:5)
    - 1864-1865 (112 items) (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Indentures, 1734, 1786 (2 items) (Box-folder 7:7)
  - James Clarkson Papers, 1771-1835 (94 items) (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Photographs, n.d. (5 items) (Box-folder 7:9)
  - Undated Material (35 items) (Box-folder 7:10)
- Series V: Oversize, 1821-1900:
  - From Series III, Political Papers (9 items) (Box-folder 8:1)
  - From Series IV, Miscellaneous (10 items) (Box-folder 8:2)